Hello and welcome back to another episode
with ItsDrdan and today we're going to
be looking at our exam number two review.
So what this video is, is this is a
recording from when me and my class in
fall of 2024 went over our exam number
two, which is for both my Saturday and
my Monday and Wednesday Chem 3A classes.
So introductory chemistry.
So the way that this review is going to
work for everybody that is watching this,
we are going to go through Canvas first.
Okay.
And talk about all the
different expectations of
really what is on the exam.
Uh, the thing I would recommend doing is
utilizing all the different markers on
the, you know, fast forward toolbar below
to be able to figure out exactly which
concepts that you want to go through.
Um, we will be doing a Kahoot!
review game if you're
interested in playing along.
The link is in the bio in this video.
You can use it.
It is a solo game that
you will be playing.
I would recommend the way to kind of
go about doing this review is watch
the review portion of it at the very
beginning, talking about what's on the
test and what you're allowed to use.
And then when you do the Kahoot!, which
is one of my old exams from a previous
semester, You can play along with it, and
then whenever you get a question wrong,
you can fast forward it to that exact
chapter marker that's inside of the video.
Okay?
So you can try to find that
exact individual piece.
So please stick along.
It's going to be a little bit of
a long video, but there's a lot of
information that's packed on it.
So I'm going to try to try to give
you hints of all the little things
that are on the exam that will really
help you get a really good grade.
Um, so when you're kind of studying,
this is a really good first benchmark.
After that, I really recommend you kind
of look at your notes, review them, then
do the practice exam, which is on Canvas.
And then afterwards, I would recommend
practicing as many problems as you can,
whether it's through practice problems
that are found via your online textbook.
Or you can convert your homeworks
into more practice problems,
or you can do practice quizzes.
The more problems that you do, the
better you will do on the exam.
Okay?
So best of luck studying, and I hope
that this review helps, and I tried
to edit it down the best that I could.
to try to make it a little bit
better and easier to follow along.
All right.
I will see you guys in the review session.
So the biggest thing is just
navigating our canvas page.
So going through the module so that way
you know where the exam study module is.
Um, it's always the first thing.
So if we minimize all this stuff
that all of you guys probably have
maximized, knowing half of you guys
didn't realize you can do this.
So I'm going to go to exam
number two study module.
First.
So as always, I put together a study
module for you guys to kind of start
off for kind of exactly what to study,
what to review when you're kind of
going through to prepare for this.
Um, if on the first exam at the
score, let's say it wasn't really
what you expected, or it was, I
don't know, better than you expected
or whatever the situation is.
Um, especially because I'm speaking
specifically to anyone that might not
have a score that they really wanted.
Um, If you were in that camp, then you
really want to think about like, what
did you do to try to really study?
Because you probably want to change that
up a little bit so that way you don't
repeat whatever might have happened.
So like if you got, if you studied for
an hour and you got like a 50, well
then clearly probably more time and
more practice is kind of really needed.
But if you studied for like 10
hours and got the that score,
then we gotta really talk about.
what methods to really study.
So the first thing I would do if it
was me and that's what we're going
to do here is obviously come to this
because that's always a good start.
But, uh, so let me tell you about what
this exam is about, what's the format
and it's because it's going to be a
little bit different than the last one.
Um, the big thing is I kind of
made it so that way it was more
favorable to award more points for
you accomplishing, you know, math.
Um, so the first thing is I think
the first, I want to say the first 18
questions are pure multiple choice,
more on, I would say con concepts,
theory, naming, swap, molar mass,
more basic type of calculations.
Um, so things that really, they
don't award partial credit.
It's only for just, you know,
like your intermolecular forces.
Can you identify something that's polar?
Can you, um, do, um, You know, swap,
drop, things like that, um, and
naming, and those kinds of things.
Uh, after that, the last ten or
so questions of, of the exam are
all questions that I ask you to
show your work for partial credit.
So there's still multiple
choice on most of them.
There's a couple that don't have
any multiple choice because it's
something that you gotta draw.
So you might be able to guess, what
could you possibly have to draw?
What have you been drawing for the last
Three weeks, um, or have you done a lab
that maybe required you to draw something?
So you might have to draw something.
Um, so with those ones, essentially,
if you show your work and it's on
the right direction, then you'll be
rewarded partial credit for kind of
essentially what you did, um, when you
were going through that specific thing.
So like, for example, if you were
doing like a mole calculation
of some type, whether it's
like empirical formula, percent
composition, like those harder ones.
And you were doing the right steps,
but maybe you just forgot to do the
end thing or maybe do some units, then,
um, then, um, you know, you'll get
partial credit for getting to that.
Um, so, uh, getting to the next
question again, I saw 1 pop up.
What are you allowed to use on this thing?
So the things that you get, right?
Um, other than the partial credit thing is
that you get access to a note card, right?
So a 3 by 5 inches note card, right?
It's a normal note card.
Um, you can put whatever
you want on it, right?
Um, you can use both sides.
The only thing I will give you is
I'll give you the yellow PROC table.
That and has, and the, whatever.
Prefixes and stuff,
references on the back.
So I'll give you the exact same
one you got in the first one.
If you want to put anything else on
it, like best spur, like naming or
notes, formulas, whatever, that's what
you'd want to put in your note cards.
So you can put as much as that
you can possibly pack on here.
Biggest thing is that you got
to be able to read it, right?
So, and know how to do it.
Usually the act of making the note card,
like if you probably do that, like, I
don't know, tomorrow or something at
some point, it kind of helps you study.
So like when you're kind of maybe
going through the review today, I would
recommend writing down like any topics
that you're like, Oh crap, I better
like really put this on my note card.
Um, so in terms of the question,
Vesper, like how much of, um,
what exact, uh, geometries do you
realistically need now, we'll tell
you when we get to those questions.
Uh, you don't need to know every single
geometry because we only really went up
to probably about row four, realistically
for 99 percent of the questions.
So it's really those basic
ones being at those are the
ones that are in biomolecules.
So when you guys get into physiology
and anatomy and start learning
about proteins and, um, enzymes and
all these other little molecules
that you find within the cells.
They're mainly just those first four.
You really don't see any of the
other stuff in any other place.
So if you need to know the VSEPR
stuff, which you probably do,
then I would recommend writing it
down for yourself so you know it.
Um, you do get, so the
electronegativity values are actually
on your yellow periodic table.
A lot of people don't
kind of realize that.
Um, so being that it's getting asked
with the different sheets, right?
What should you exactly really write down?
Let's go through them real quick
because it's not a bad thing
to talk about in the handouts.
Um, so you'll get the
yellow PR table, right?
That's the one thing that
I said I'll give you.
So with the lecture negativity
values, they are on here, right?
Which not everybody realizes.
So just to point out to everybody,
um, I pointed out into the Monday,
Wednesday class, but you know,
Saturday, I don't get to see you.
So if you guys don't get that, uh,
Experience, but if you look at right
at the bottom of the bottom right
of any of these different blocks,
you'll see that that electronegativity
value is right here at the bottom.
So it's on all these elements.
So it is there.
It's just, you know, I think even for
me, I didn't even realize it was there
until like my second or third semester
teaching here, which is kind of sad.
I didn't know.
So it's jammed there.
I never seen it on a
periodic table like that.
It's really nice.
So it's already on there.
Um, that way, you know, um, and
then it's on all the elements.
So you got that there.
So you have that.
So with Vesper, though, um, really,
you only need to know, I would say
the geometries in this top corner.
So just this area.
in purple.
You don't need to know any
of the ones below that.
We never really saw any of them.
So it's just six, six structures.
It's not too bad, um,
compared to all of them.
Uh, so I'm only, if I'm going to give
you geometry, it's only one of the six.
Um, if I'll double check the exam, if
it, if there is one that's not, then
I'll have either, I'll give you, make
sure you have the Vesper sheet, but it's
only going to be in this top left corner.
It's all triple check.
So only these ones.
So not too bad.
So if you want to put them on another
card, you can, um, I wouldn't blame you.
It's, you know, it's probably pretty easy.
You want to fit somewhere on there,
um, for what they look like or how you
want to figure out whether you want
to put groups or lone pairs or however
you've been, you know, doing that.
Are there any questions
about the dispersion, dipole,
dipole and hydrogen bonding?
I may ask What would, what do you think?
Do you think I would, do you think I
would spend, um, multiple days talking
about it if it would be on there?
And the answer is yeah, right.
It, it is gonna be on there.
So not to be, you know, a jerk
about it, but it, it will be on.
Um, so if those are things that you need
to know those definitions, like for what
they are, put that on there, but keep in
mind, like, this is more when it comes
to using a note card, the way you want to
make sure you use it is that you can find
things, organize it well, and it's more
of like a crutch, you don't want to use
it as like your life support for the test,
because that is the only thing, like, you
never studied anything, that's the only
thing you're using, it's going to explode
so far, and like, in everybody's face.
So use it as something that
you're like, Oh, I'm like, not as
good at remembering this thing.
You know, put that on there.
Like, so you have it, but usually I
think like 90 percent of my students
that end up doing note cards, you end up
not needing it cause you wrote it down.
So you can't even remember it.
It's usually just a reference.
Um, so you'll get the yellow sheet.
So you get all that stuff.
Um, so you'll have like your temperature
formulas, which is probably like the
one thing to kind of keep in mind.
Like that's already on here.
You already have, I think, so you
have, um, the value for how to
convert, um, joules to calories.
So if you have to do that
one, it's already on here.
Um, so for the thermo chem stuff, uh,
and then I, yeah, so with your dispersion
and all that stuff, then I would
recommend making sure you're kind of
semi familiar with how to identify them.
And we'll talk about how to do them when
we're kind of going through questions.
And then the green sheet, so the
only ions that you need to know,
um, so I checked, is the oxyanions.
So these are the only ones.
So if you remember the T4 3 method,
right, so we kind of, we've talked
about that before, so I'm just
highlighting the colors for the T4
3, then you will be okay, right?
So those are the only
ones that are on there.
are these ones.
Um, the, any other polyatomics that
are on the exam, I tell you the
name and I give you the formula.
So I give you both.
So that way you have it.
Okay.
So it's only these ones that, uh,
this, uh, these are the ones that
I would recommend memorizing.
Because, like I've said to Monday,
Wednesday, a couple times now, is that
if you don't know them by the time you
do chemical reactions, or when you're
doing chemical reactions, which Saturday
you started doing chemical reactions
to, then it's gonna make it ten times
harder, um, to be able to balance these
formulas easily, because you're kind
of jumbling through thirty reference
sheets when you're going through them.
So put them on note cards if you
haven't just to kind of study them.
Right?
So you already have to
have one three by five.
So that means you probably
have another 99 in the pack.
Uh, so I would recommend putting
them on flashcards or memorizing
the T43 method, whichever helps.
Um, and if you don't know what
I'm talking about, the T43 method,
go to my video that's on it.
Just go to the, it's
in our canvas modules.
Um, for how to memorize it, or we
can go over it later if need be to
that's fine too, but I didn't put any
of these, uh, modifier ones on there.
So I made it not so bad canvas.
Right?
So the big thing is here.
Right, so, uh, make sure you
bring your scantron so you need
the same scantron as last time.
So hopefully, uh, I think last time I
told her, but it by, you know, a couple
just so they had enough for the semester.
Um, so 9, is the code for it.
Um, I'll make sure that there are
extras in case anyone forgot it, but
you know, try not to make it a habit.
You know, if you did borrow one
from me in the past, or then,
Try to bring one back next time.
Pay it forward for another student.
Uh, other stuff that's here too.
So I have, um, uh, the study guide here.
There's a practice exam.
I put flashcards up here as well too.
So if you don't have time to
make flashcards, the study terms
and things like that, then, um,
they're already here for you.
So you can print them and cut
them out or, or just kind of
review them if you'd like to.
So you have that available.
Um, but from their, um, big thing to kind
of point out is, um, you know, I'm going
to get asked this by at least 5 people.
This is not an actual assignment
that you got to, like, turn in
for exam number 2 study guide.
It's just purely there.
That's where your grades going
to go when you do the exam.
So everybody hears that.
It's just where I'm going
to put the grade afterwards.
So I know it says 100 points, but that's
where your exam grade goes because.
With the study guide, I try to
boil every chapter down to like
the most, um, important concepts.
So I made this thing based off of Our exam
and then also like off my previous exam.
So like things that might
end up on the final exam.
So it's like whether you need it
for now or you need it for later.
So that way you have it somewhere.
Um, when it comes to this test, the
biggest thing for chapter 4, it really
wasn't that much of it on the 1st exam.
Um, I tried to actually not put
that much on there just because for
a lot of you learning naming is.
It's honestly very overwhelming, right?
It's a lot.
Um, that blue handout, right?
That whole entire flow chart, like
maybe you're starting to get it down
and you kind of start to, you're able
to do it without looking at it if you
are incredible, but it's a, it takes
a long time to be able to develop
that language of chemical formulas.
That's probably the biggest thing is
there's going to be a lot of little
naming questions and, um, whether it's.
Identifying like what
kind of compound it is.
Is it ionic?
Is it covalent?
Um, that's probably going to be the
biggest thing is can you do things
whether it's from a formula and make
a name or go from a name to a formula.
Um, there's probably at least I
would say three to five questions
at least evolving around that.
So you kind of like, you know,
that's a good chunk of points.
Um, especially if you think
there's only like 30 questions.
That's 20 percent of the
points could be from naming.
Um, so it's probably 1 of the bigger,
bigger areas that had questions
to it was with the naming stuff.
Um, after that, when it comes to chapter
4, technically, it's from chapter 4, but
we didn't talk about it until chapter
7, but the, uh, uh, phase changes are
technically part of that chapter to,
um, make sure, you know, your phase
changes, at least, especially like that.
So there's 6 phase changes.
So make sure you're okay with,
like, uh, boiling, freezing,
um, uh, you know, melting.
Condensation, sublimation, deposition,
and I feel like I missed one.
Is that all of them?
Oh, maybe.
I missed all of them.
So you want to make sure you remember
all six of them that are there.
Um, if, uh, you need practice, so you have
a lot of options to practice problems.
Um, realistically, for most
people, reading your notes is
never enough to get a good grade.
in Chem 3A or in physio
or anatomy or microbiome.
It's usually like the first step.
It's like the first hour you go through
your notes and you kind of figure
out some of the things you need.
But you realistically need to kind of
practice as many problems as possible,
which is reason why you have so
much homework with so many problems.
It's not to make you suffer.
It's just because as you can see, it
really takes a lot of practice to kind
of get an inkling of what's going on.
And even then you're like, still
aren't even, we're still not even
sure sometimes what's going on.
It's, it's a lot.
Um, so you can either 1 of the
things I have here is I have, uh, the
recommended end of the chapter problems.
So that go to our online textbook, right?
If you.
Didn't realize, right?
We do have our online textbook
on the right hand side, right?
That you can click on at any point.
So, if the videos aren't clear,
or lecture isn't clear, or.
I'm not clear, try to read that, read
the individual chapter of the textbook.
They're usually only like a
couple pages for each section.
It's usually a pretty quick read,
and there's a lot of examples in
it, too, that are ones that I didn't
use in class or in lecture or in
videos, so it's not a bad thing.
Like, you know, reading sucks
sometimes, but, uh, that's kind
of honestly how I learned chem.
My professor was amazing, but a lot of
times not the best explainer of things.
So, you know, reading was what saved it.
And there's a lot of examples that
show you exactly how to do the problem.
Um, so I picked out problems
that specifically are like ones
that we either do in homework or
that would be like on the test.
Um, after that, so chapter
five, a big thing is with this
one, mole conversions, right?
We had three major mole conversions.
You need to know how
to do all three, right?
There's molar mass, so make sure you're
comfortable with knowing how to go
from grams to moles or moles to grams.
Uh, make sure you're okay with,
um, trying to set up those types
of problems and how to find molar
mass using your periodic table.
Then after that is the mole to mole
ratio, which is probably going to be
the second most important conversion
in the class because it uses the
subscripts to go from one element Right?
So if you had like something like,
um, I don't know, C3H6, right?
As a molecule, right?
That means you have three moles
of carbon, six moles of hydrogen,
as like an example, right?
And that's a ratio you can define.
Um, so that's really good.
Uh, Avogadro's number, right?
It's only for particles,
molecules, things like that.
We probably will never really see
it again after this, this chapter,
because it's something that's used
very sparingly because you don't
really We relate it to mass, right?
We work in a physical world.
Avogadro's number, we'll use it for
now as a conversion to bridge the gap
to theory, but we're mainly using mole
conversions, the other ones, right?
But you still got to be able to use it.
So make sure you're okay with that.
Probably the hardest thing that
comes from this chapter is when we
go over the review problems, is doing
empirical formulas and mass percents,
which percents are kind of scary.
They're kind of hard.
I'm finding out that a lot of you really,
really struggle with the idea of how
to use a Um, just from, you know, maybe
gaps and like your math background.
Um, so practice percents
as much as you can.
There's going to be at least 1 problem.
That's a mass percent problem.
Same thing with an empirical
formula problem as well.
Uh, so make sure you have
some familiarity about it.
You don't want to just use as a toss away.
You can even put, like, the step by
step on how to solve them on your
note card if you want, you know, the.
There's no limit to
what you can put on it.
So if you want to have a little
procedure for yourself for how to
do each type of problem, you know,
that's an option that you can do.
So it just kind of depends on how,
how have you been kind of working
through all your homework and
videos and all that stuff, right?
You have choices.
So that, I mean, that's what I
did whenever I got a new card.
I would just put like the step by
step on it outside of the references.
And you can fit a lot on these things too.
And the other thing is too, a
lot of people never think about
is you can type this up too.
Um, you can actually set up a word
document to be a three by five inches.
When you type it and you can change
the font size, so if it's better
for you to type, which I know some
of you submit your notes that are
typed already intent for those of you
that do that, you could easily copy
and paste things to your note card.
So, Google, Google Docs or
on word, you can do that.
And if anyone's like, how
the hell do you do it?
I will gladly tell you if you dismiss me.
Um, So with Lewis structures and
intermolecular forces, yes you need to
know your intermolecular forces, you
need to be able to draw Lewis structures.
There will be a few Lewis structure
questions on the test, being that we had
a lab on it, we had a homework on it, um,
luckily MyOpenMath is not involved with
it, so you don't have to struggle bus
over if the dots are in the right box, or
did you put them back when you were done.
That's not a thing, it's just
drawing them out yourself.
So either know your valence electrons,
or know how to, the bonding trends, one
or the other, whatever method works for
you, you will have to, um, go through
that process of trying to draw it.
Um, so I would, I would really recommend
just, um, practicing as much as you
can, um, so that way there's at least,
I want to say, four Lewis structures,
I think, on there, and a couple
more on the fill in the blank area.
So, and then withdrawing them and you
label them as polar or non polar, right?
And then that would lead to their
molecular forces too, right?
It's all related, um, which
is that that's when you use
your electronegativity values.
So if you need a little step by step
on how to do that on your note card,
that's something you can write out.
Um,
let's see.
I didn't really put a lot of
the prediction stuff on there.
Being that with Monday and
Wednesday, I didn't really talk
about it with them that much.
I just made them watch
one of the videos on it.
And same thing on Saturday.
I mean, that's what you do is
watch videos all day for it.
Um, there's not really, I don't
know if there's any predictions.
The only thing I might've said is like,
which one's like the strongest force
that might be possible type of question.
Like, so if you have a molecule,
like what is the strongest force?
Um, I don't think I had, if
there is any comparisons, it
might be off like dispersion.
So like member dispersion was the bigger
the molecule, the more dispersion.
Um, so that polarizability or, um,
there's like a list of molecules, maybe
ranking them in order for strength.
Which means, like, you could,
uh, label, like, what's hydrogen
bonding, like, you're looking for
those, you remember, ethanol, right?
You're looking for fluorine,
nitrogen, oxygen, connect to a
hydrogen, so, like, things like that.
You're going through them.
And if you want to practice
them, once again, I do have
a bunch of practice problems.
Uh, thermo, I actually kind of brought
thermo back a hair, just because
it's a lot of math, it's a little
overwhelming, and uh, I don't know.
It's kind of, we really honestly don't
use it a ton outside of Chapter 7.
There's, you might see it a little
bit here and there when it comes
to the specific heat conversions.
But when trying to think about what do
you need the most to prepare most, you
want to do nursing or biology as a major.
What do you need most moving forward?
And honestly, I don't see how
thermochemistry is 1 of those things.
So, um, I'm trying to think of
really, it's like looking at.
Asking myself, all my students
that have ever take that.
So that, like, that still talk to
me too much from previous semesters.
I'm like, what do you need for physio?
So I'm trying to mainly focus on
those things because I don't want
you struggling in physio because it's
such, it's such an overwhelming course.
It's I, they all say it's harder than
chem three, a, which is shocking to me
because this, I make this a lot of work.
Um, so it's, yeah.
You kind of, kind of got to make
sure you're okay with all that
chem knowledge and bio knowledge
before getting there, right?
There's a reason why it's a
prereq to prepare you for it.
Um, but the big thing is to make
sure you're okay with doing the
temperature conversions and then
just a specific heat calculations.
So, like, any variation of specific
heat, whether it's, um, just
using the MCAT equation, solving
maybe for temperature, solving for
specific heat, solving for mass.
Okay.
using that MCAT equation.
That's really the big thing.
Um, maybe it might be solving for
final or initial temperature, right?
In class and in the lecture videos
we had to rearrange the formula.
You might have to be okay
with doing that, right?
You need to be okay with algebra.
Um, so that's really probably the only
thing other than just phase changes,
you know, labeling a phase change.
I did not put any of the Delta
H fusion or any of the Delta H
vaporization problems on there.
And there is no, uh, heating cooling
curve problem with multiple Pieces on it.
So there's gonna be no like Q1 plus
Q2 plus Q3, you know, equals q, total
energy, there's gonna be none of those.
Um, they're, they're a little too
hard, uh, for this, but they could
be on the team assessment though.
So, um, being that after the exam
you will have the team assessment,
but you get to struggle bus with your
partner, so, and you have your notes
for that, so it's a little different.
Um, if it's on there, I'm still making it,
so I haven't decided what's on there yet.
Okay, so that's that
right with the module.
Are there any like questions about
like any of that stuff so far?
I know it's a lot of just me talking,
kind of hand waving at the moment, but um,
that's kind of my thoughts with the exam.
I'm just trying to give you
hints of what's really on it in
terms of how to study, right?
So obviously you got to ask yourself
what you did last time because
maybe it worked, maybe it didn't.
If it didn't work, if it did not work,
the thing I would do if it was me is I
would read my notes first just to kind
of refresh my brain from my, yeah, my
brain of everything you've been really
talking about over the last four weeks.
And it really went hurt of just kind
of skimming through your chapter
one through four, three notes
as well, because a lot of those
skills you're probably using still.
Yeah.
Especially sig figs, percents, math,
um, in general, and maybe even atoms
and ions, like if any of that stuff
is a struggle, review it, kind of just
look through it, skim through it just
so that you're like seeing it again.
It kind of helps.
That's step one.
After that, what I would recommend kind of
doing is, um, I would say it might be, um,
um, Better to take their time and really
probably go through the practice exam
would probably be one of the first things.
So I do have a practice exam on
canvas that you have available
so you can go through that one.
That one is an old exam.
So that one is from all of 2023,
so it's from last year.
It's a little bit harder than yours is.
a little bit.
Um, there's a lot more, um, there's
like Delta H fusion vaporization stuff
on there and some, uh, prediction
stuff for intermolecular forces,
which I didn't put on our exam.
Just because, like, the
students then struggled with it.
And I'm like, I feel like I
see the trend every semester.
So I'm like, why?
Why make it harder on you?
There's no point.
So, uh, I'm not going to that ones.
You don't have to really worry about
too much if you're not able to get it,
but it might be on the team assessment.
So if you want to know how to
do it, it's not bad practice.
Um, after that, obviously you
want to finish all your homework
assignments as soon as possible.
If you're still like watching
videos and finishing homeworks the
day before the test, it's kind of
spelling out a recipe for disaster.
So I would recommend trying to
finish as much of it as possible
at least two days before.
So that way you're not just spending
all this time just trying to get
done the, you know, the fundamentals.
You want to be able to review things
and absorb information versus just
kind of like, you I don't know,
only focusing on one thing, right?
That's kind of one of the, one of
the downfalls for a lot of you.
It's really easy to fall
behind in this class.
You, you know, you miss a day and
then it feels like you missed a month.
It's one of those courses.
Um, just because we do so
much, uh, every single week.
So, I personally would recommend,
uh, trying to either, you could re
watch videos if you want, uh, it
just depends on like how well do you
remember the questions, if you want
to re do them, then you could do that,
but if you kind of remember them,
there's no point in doing it again.
Um, it's more about fresh, new problems.
So the one thing that a lot of
people don't realize is that you
can actually convert your old
homeworks to practice homeworks.
So if, um, let's see if I can find
one of them, just as an example.
So let's say I kind of, uh,
bring up, um, this old one.
So I have week three's homework.
This one's not on the test,
right, um, looking at it.
But as you can see, like I'm in
a student view, so like I could
redeem five late passes to open it
back up, or I can click practice.
So the thing is, what does
practice do when you click that?
Is it opens up a blank homework, it locks
the assignment, so keep that in mind.
So if you're not done it, do not click it.
Um, so if you're finished, if
you click it, you're already
done, it's already graded anyway.
So you can, it gives you a brand
new homework, it doesn't affect
your grade, you can just do whatever
problems you want to practice.
You don't have to complete all 30 of
them, you can just do like a couple of
them just to see, hey, do you know it?
And if you want, you can always
ask for similar questions.
So keep in mind, a lot of them
shuffle through new numbers,
new problems, new questions.
So it's the thing that not a lot of
people realize is like the practice
button, it can give you a new problems.
So if you're ever like, Oh, I
wish he gave us more problems.
I'm like, you got them here.
Here you go.
Um, your wish, your wish is my command.
So that's one thing.
The other thing that a lot of people don't
realize, so this one is Monday, Wednesday
class, so it looks a little bit different
than Saturday, as a disclaimer, is that
at the end of a lot of the modules,
I'm trying to find one, is that there's
practice quizzes that are available, too.
So, for example, at the end of,
uh, chapter, or chapter six, for
molecular shape, I have a quiz
that you can take that pulls, I
think, ten questions at a time.
From a completely different bank
of questions that none of you
have even probably have seen yet.
So it's like another 80 to 100 questions.
So you can just do try 10 of them.
See how you do.
If you really struggling with struggling
with moles, naming and forces, then this
is a really good one to multiple choice,
which is what your exam is going to be.
It's going to be multiple choice.
So that way you can practice that.
Um, I think I have quizzes.
I want to say quiz number six, I think.
I'm gonna be five is less one.
So I think it's practice five
and four, I think, for this one.
So there's a couple of them.
Um, after that, you could have, you have
the textbook problems available too.
So that's probably anywhere from,
you know, 200 to 500 problems.
So for anyone that's like an a plus plus
overachiever, that's like, I want more.
You got it.
And for anyone that's
like, I just want to pass.
Well, you still need to
practice problems, right?
Um, you got it too.
So focus on what you don't know.
Right?
Um, so when you're doing the practice
exam, write down whenever there's a
problem that you feel like you had to,
like, Look it up, you had to look through
your notes, you feel like you didn't
get, because those are the concepts that
either you want to write down on your
note card for how to do it, or you need
to study it and do more problems with it.
One of the things I'm kind of starting
to realize, which is kind of the
curse of MyOpenMath, it's a, it's a
blessing and a curse, that program.
It's great because it tells you if you're
right, if you do the problem correctly.
That's fantastic.
Get instant feedback.
It's faster than I could ever grade.
But the curse is that, you know,
if you get the checkbox and
you're like, Oh, I got it right.
You got to ask yourself, do
you understand the problem?
Okay, do you really get it?
Because, you know, if you're like, Oh,
I must get it because I got it right.
That's probably does not mean you got it.
You probably should try another
one and just to really make
sure that you're able to do it.
So if you kind of see yourself
doing that a lot on the practice,
that means you need to review it.
Um, you need to understand it, not
just be able to, um, regurgitate,
you know, you can't just, you can't
just memorize your way through Chem.
It's, it's, it's not like bio.
It's, it's, it's not just
memorize this textbook.
Um, you can't do that through Chem.
Unfortunately, I wish you could.
I wish that was the
answer, but it's sadly not.
It's too much math to do it that way.
Yeah.
And then, um, one thing too is, uh,
the Kahoot that we'll go through.
Yeah.
It is an old test to,
um, it is my exam from
ring of last semester.
So spring 24.
So it's my most recent test.
Um, well, almost my most recent, I
guess I taught a summer class, but
so this one's a pretty recent one.
So, um, I converted it to a code
so that way you guys can see kind
of what I had in mind back then.
Um, it's pretty similar to
the difficulty of yours.
Um, there was a few things I might
have tweaked here and there when
I was kind of typing them in.
I'm like, oh, I guess this one, huh, okay.
So if there are another
questions, we can go through that.
So we'll go as long as like people
kind of have questions, need
help, um, as you kind of see it.
So let me kind of bring that up
and then you guys can join it.
So, um, okay.
So, and you guys can use your,
you can use your reference sheets.
But kind of one thing I would recommend
is when you're going through any of
these, try to, um, If there's something
you don't know, just write down the topic
for yourself so you know what to study.
Alright, so I'm gonna start
by getting this one right.
So with this one, the whole thing
with this kind of question, sorry
about that, is doing your swap drop,
right, is the entire idea here.
So, remembering your
charges is key, right?
You're gonna have a blank new PROC table.
So if you need to write down charges,
I kind of hope by this point you don't
have to, but for aluminum, you might need
to just because it's part of the steps.
Right.
So if I were to just kind of quick,
real quick, just, uh, all right.
So for the first problem, what we're going
to be quickly doing is swap dropping.
So the thing that's so common that
students can forget is that when
we're looking at aluminum, right?
So this one is in the plus three column.
So this is the first value in our
steps when it comes to our cations.
So it has a predictable charge.
So, we have aluminum, then we have
zinc, right, and then our next step
is silver, so what this is going
to be is plus three, plus two,
and plus one, so one, two, three.
And then oxygen, right, so when we're
looking at these, right, nitrogen is
negative three, oxygen is negative
two, and fluorine is negative one,
so all's we're simply going to do
is we're going to take our aluminum.
Right, so it'd be aluminum 3 and
then we're going to then have
oxygen 2 and we're going to trade
the numbers, so the 2 is going to
come down to aluminum, and then the
3 is going to come next to oxygen.
So what are we going to end up having?
So we'll rewrite it, and we have
aluminum 2, and then oxygen 2.
oxygen 3 for our next one, right?
So we see that those subscripts are
being traded, and as a result it
balances the ionic charge of our formula.
So this is our swap drop.
Right, so this is something
you need to make sure that you
remember for this exam and for
when we balance chemical reactions.
Okay, so if you do get a problem like
this, I'm not gonna tell the answer,
but if you do get one, I would highly
recommend you draw it, unless you're
really good at knowing bond trends.
If you're not, then draw it, so that way
you make sure you get the correct answer.
You don't want to just kind of pick
the one that looks right, like that's
A recipe for disaster and I can there's
probably some people will try to do that.
And if you are running out
of time, great strategy.
But if you have, like, an hour,
then make sure you go through it.
And okay.
Oh, wonderful.
Everybody got it.
Oh, that's fantastic.
I love it.
So, um, with this one, right, just
kind of showing it, um, Really,
if you know bonding trends, it
makes this problem really easy.
Um, carbon makes four bonds, right?
So what does that really mean is that,
well, it needs to somehow satisfy
that requirement, so it needs the two
double bonds to make that possible.
And sulfur needs two bonds,
so it fits really, really
well in that situation, right?
Because it, because it can do that.
All right, so double points.
All right, according to the VSEPR
model, the molecular geometry of
the carbonate ion would be what?
This one's kind of a hard one.
You might have had the
misfortune of having to do
this problem on your homework.
It was one of the, uh, extra credit
ones depending on which one you got.
Either you got this
one or you got nitrate.
It was one or the other.
Oh, speaking of which, there's
gonna be no resonance on the
test, so don't worry about that.
Okay, so drawing the carbonate
ion is a very hard example.
You might have had that misfortune of
getting this assigned to you as a homework
question and it was an extra credit one.
But it is very tough just because
it has resonance to it, and it has
an ionic charge, so what do you do?
So the first thing that we're gonna
do is we're gonna write our carbon,
being that's our central atom.
It's the atom that can make the most
friends, it can make four different bonds.
So the first thing we're gonna do is
we're gonna draw an oxygen on each
side, and then we're gonna assign
its six electrons around it, and
we're gonna draw all six of them.
Okay, so we're putting
its six valence electrons.
Around each one.
And then what we'll do is we're going
to connect them with a single bond.
So we're gonna connect
each carbon to oxygen.
Now, in the process, you're
gonna see that none of these
different elements are happy.
Carbon only has a one extra electron
that it can bond to something.
So what we'll do is we'll pick one
of the oxygens to make a double bond.
So, okay, we have that.
Now, one thing about these is
the oxygens are still not happy.
They have this lone electron
that's available to it.
So what do we got to do?
Well, you got to keep in mind
that this original molecule at the
very, very top It had a two minus
charge, which what does that mean?
It means it has two extra electrons as
so many extra that's extra negative.
So what we're going to end up
doing is we're going to add
those to the exterior atoms.
The more electronegative elements that
we're missing to complete their octet.
So as a result, you can see that,
um, if you look at one of these
oxygens on the side, they now have
a total of all seven, or sorry, all
eight of its lone pair electrons.
So it ends up being very, very happy,
um, with all of its valence electrons.
So now the next part was how
do you assign the geometry?
So what we do is we have our central
atom here in the middle, and what
we're going to end up doing is
highlighting each of the groups
that surround that central atom.
So how many do we end up having?
Well, we have one, two, three
groups around our central atom,
three groups, zero lone pairs.
So what we're going to end up doing
is we're going to go up, back up
to our, sorry, our VSEPR chart.
So once we do that here, Uh,
we're going to find our three
groups with, uh, no lone pairs.
So when we do that, right, we have
three groups right here, no lone pairs.
So where are we going to go is right here.
So what does that tell you?
You have a trigonal
planar geometry for C03.
Two minus, and this structure does have
two other resonant structures as well.
It's something you might
need to know for your final.
I did not put it on this exam.
It could be found also on
the team assessment, which
might be possible as well.
All right, let's go on
to the next problem.
It's like, what happened to the music?
I'm like, okay.
So, um, with this one, right,
you guys got it really quickly.
So that's good.
Um, so hydrogen bonding, right,
is kind of the big thing.
So you're looking for a simple
trend is what you're trying to find.
Okay.
Right, so if you can find OH, or
remember I said find FNO, right,
is the whole idea, so OH, NH.
If you see OH, NH, or FH in a molecule
that are next to each other in the
formula, it can do hydrogen bonding.
So with this one, right with
methanol, which is the one in yellow
here, you see that it does have
that, um, uh, that entire, um, uh,
you have the, the, that OH signature
that was on, on that particular one.
Let me stop sharing.
So that way it comes back up.
Okay.
But OH is kind of the idea here.
So with hydrogen bonding, it
has to follow that definition.
Um, whereas the other ones,
you're just looking for something
electronegative for dipole dipole.
And then dispersion means it's nonpolar,
is really the thing that you're
looking for with uh, for R class.
But keep in mind that all molecules
can do dispersion, even polar
ones can, but it's the only thing
that the nonpolar ones can do.
Which one of the following is polar?
And sometimes you have to draw
them too, if you have to, you
know, go through and do it, it
would make it a long problem, but.
It's better to do it correctly
than to blindly guess type thing.
There is a trick to this
one, believe it or not.
So let's kind of talk about it.
So let me write down all of the, actually
I guess I will have it to the side.
So, one of the things is when we, uh,
did these in class or in videos for
Saturday, Um, there was a couple little
credentials that you kind of like would
check off to figure out if something
was, um, um, what do you call it?
If it was nonpolar or
not was the entire idea.
So, uh, going to my tablet, the one
thing is with this one is if you can
see an atom has all the same elements
all around it, then that means it's
considered to be nonpolar, right?
So what do I mean by that?
Well, if I kind of draw these really
quick, so if I have like CO2, for
example, Right, that one is evenly
pulling from oxygens on both sides.
The CBr4, even though CBr is
very polar, but when you end up
drawing it, you see that it's all
the same element on all sides.
Same thing with CH, same
thing, same element, all sides.
Um, the only one, so even F, right,
so that's a very polar atom, but
remember whenever it's the exact same
element, they cancel each other out.
So even if you say like, oh, 4.
0, 4.
0, they subtract and it makes a big zero.
So the only one that has something
different about it, which even if
you're not quick is you see that
there's this one little atom.
It takes the power of one atom to
make the whole thing different.
So CHBR in this case, so if I
kind of maybe just change this
one structure over here and I put
a little H, well now it's full.
It's all pulling in the direction.
Downwards.
So it's pulling towards the bromines.
That changes polarity.
So if we were to look at this and
think of reviewing, cause you know,
a couple of intermolecular forces,
well, what forces can these do?
So once they are nonpolar,
they do dispersion.
So you're going to see that all the ones
that canceled all do dispersion, right?
So all the ones that, um, pretty much all
of, uh, These guys all over here, right?
All these will do dispersion, whereas
this one, the question is, well,
does it do hydrogen bonding or not?
That's your first criteria.
If it can do hydrogen bonding,
you know what it is, right?
So remember, if no, if you see
an electronegative difference.
Or a very electronegative
atom, then that's when it
would do, um, dipole dipole.
So in this case, we
would have dipole dipole.
That's a tough one.
It's really tough for you
if you didn't get it right.
Don't, don't worry.
It's the, it's how we learn, right?
I'd rather you make mistakes
and learn from them.
Um, what is the predicted molecular
geometry of the CH4 molecule
according to the VSEPR model?
So, I just drew it.
Let's see if you can remember
what the trolling was.
Maybe you wrote it down for yourself.
You guys are just too good.
Alright, so, um, CH4.
Four groups.
No lone pairs on it.
So, just to kind of, for the video's sake.
I know you guys got it right,
but I think it's, I know a lot
of you guys do use this video.
I was actually shocked how many
people watched it for the last one.
So let's just look at it
just so we can kind of see.
All right, so the big thing is,
is when you're drawing this,
right, you have the four groups.
So even if you're not an expert
at drawing VSEPR, that's fine.
You can draw the Lewis structure.
But you do need to know
how to count groups.
So we do have one, We have two,
we have three, we have four.
So we count bonds and loan pairs
attached to the central atom.
So just as a little reminder, right?
This guy here is central.
It's in the middle.
That's what you're looking for.
Um, so all's we're going to do is
we're going to go down to four groups,
and then we have zero lone pairs.
So what does that mean?
Is that our molecule in
this case is tetrahedral.
All right.
Helium atoms do not combine to form
helium two molecules, yet helium
atoms do attract one another weakly
through which intermolecular force?
This is when in class and
the videos we talked about
something called polarizability.
And I kind of used a, maybe not the best
example of using coin flips to describe
which side the electrons would be on.
Okay, so with this one, um,
how exactly can you look at it?
So, it's a noble gas.
The noble gases, right, are,
they have a complete octet.
They're on the very right
side of your periodic table.
Sorry, I'm like pointing this way
and it's going left of your screen,
right side of your periodic table.
Um, so being that it's on that far
side, that means that it's something
that it doesn't need electrons.
So it doesn't bond typically
with different elements.
Um, so it can still do dispersion
because you remember if a molecule
kind of bumps another molecule,
What happens is the electron cloud
kind of shifts it as a result.
So if you kind of think yourself
slamming on your brakes, right?
You are on electron in your car.
You shift forward as a result of that
forward momentum of your car, how much
it had before the brakes were hit.
But when that happens, it takes some
time for you to kind of fix yourself
up because you're like, Oh God, you
know, heart's racing a little bit.
Same thing with electrons.
They just hit another atom.
That's scary.
So, whenever it's something that's non
polar, or a noble gas, or a diatomic
gas, like let's say any of the seven
diatomics, they do dispersion, okay?
So dispersion is when we talk
about non polar elements.
And like I said, if at any point you
guys have questions about the, this
intermolecular force stuff, that's
like, it's still not quite making sense.
So which of the following is defined as an
attractive force between polar molecules?
So which one would be considered an
Is there a link to place?
Yeah, yeah, there will be a link to
put in the in the, uh, the modules.
So, um, it will be so 1 thing I probably
should have mentioned this earlier is
like, if you're not able to, whether
we get through this all, I don't know.
Depends on how many people are
here towards the end of it.
But, um, 1 thing that I was really
recommending, because this, like I said,
this was an old test is so the link will
be in the YouTube bio for the video.
And then it will also be
in, um, on canvas as well.
So you can kind of like play along and
let's see, you don't get one, right?
I've been putting chapter markers in
the video so that way you can quickly
find, um, exactly which question
you want to, you want to review.
Um, it might take me until, probably
until the end of tomorrow to I'm going
to edit tonight, I'll probably post it
tomorrow, and then I'll probably put
the chapter markers Thursday night,
probably, because editing a two to three
hour recording is a nightmare, I found
out last time, but I did get it done.
So I'll get it as fast as I can, um, with
whatever sleep I can get muster out of it.
But yes, there will All right, so
it looks like this one you guys are
split, which actually that's okay
because even for the people that picked
yellow you I believe were Correct.
So which was number two.
So with this one, it's kind of
a trick question Sort of it.
So one of the things is When they're
polar, you are all correct, it does
dipole dipole, no denying that.
But you have to remember that every
molecule does dispersion, right?
Every single one of them.
So, uh, with that in mind, right,
that's, uh, some, I feel like you
had one where you had to list all
the forces the molecule can do.
It's strongest is dipole dipole, however,
it can also do dispersion, right, as well.
So that's something to kind of like
keep in mind with this particular video.
So going through every
single piece of information.
So dipole dipole is the
strongest, then dispersion.
In order for it to do ion dipole
interactions, it would have to
be, um, solvating something.
So you know how in lab, uh, so Monday,
Wednesday, when we had lab this week,
we did the chemical reactions lab,
and we used the solubility tables.
Those are talking about ions being
formed, and that's due to water.
Making an ion dipole interaction
and solvating and ripping apart
ionic bonds like phone books.
Um, which of the following
molecules is non polar?
So another one about polarity.
I put a lot more intermolecular, I
put some extra intermolecular force
questions in this just because, um,
a lot of you messaging me about them.
The trick with these is typically,
um, geometry is one, right?
So if you have like the same element
all around the molecule, then It's
a good chance that it's nonpolar,
however, you have to check, does the
central atom, does it have lone pairs?
If it does have lone pairs, then
that means it's polar, right?
So for Chem 3A, that definition
works pretty well, right?
And even if any of you go to
tutoring, um, drop in tutoring, I've
been hearing a lot of the drop in
tutors have been saying that too.
It's true about like 95 percent of
the time that you can go off the
lone pairs off the central atom.
There are examples, we've done examples
in class where that's not true.
You know, make sure you do check the
electronegativity too, for lone pairs,
you can quickly look at the values.
PH3, it looks like it should
be polar, but it's not.
So this one was like, across the board,
every pick something, see what we got.
All right, so CO2, we
drew that one before.
All right, so that one was a linear
molecule when we were looking at that.
So if I, uh, quickly kind of,
uh, share my tablet, just so
we can kind of talk about it.
Um, so that one, right, was the
linear, it was a linear molecule.
So we had it up here on
the top, uh, the top left.
So we also have NH3.
So if you kind of remember, nitrogen
has five valence electrons to it.
So it's, that means it's going to
have a lone pair on that central atom.
Um, even though it's bonding to the
three hydrogens on each side, you
can see that it has one lone pair.
So that's, you can take that one out.
That one's polar.
Um, CH3Cl, you can take that
one out because that is, has one
atom that's different and it's
chlorine, which is very polar.
Water, uh, hopefully, you
know, water's polar, right?
It can do hydrogen bonding.
So if it can do hydrogen
bonding, very, very polar.
So we can rule that one out.
Um, OF two is actually very similar
to water, but once again, you got the
two lone pairs on oxygen, and then
you have the florian on each side.
That one's slightly polar too, so
that's kind of all the molecules there.
So the only one is CO2.
The total number of loan
pairs in NCL three is,
so if this one, you have to
draw the Lewis structure.
And then make sure you put all your
lone pairs and you want to count every
pair and you think you can do without
drawing it, then super impressive.
That means you're very well
practiced and you know how to do
it, which may be some of you do.
That's possible.
So, so it looks like most of
you guys got this one, right?
With this one, right?
First thing you want to draw is nitrogen.
It's your central atom because
it can make the most friends.
It can make three bonds, whereas
chlorine can only make one bond.
So what we're going to
chlorines on all sides.
So with its seven valence electrons,
and where we got seven was from
the row of the periodic table,
right, so keep that in mind too.
So if you want to, I can show you guys
that just to review the valence electrons.
So we're going to, uh, draw the
structure, we're going to connect it
all together, and now we're connected,
we're going to count how many lone pairs.
So we got one, two, three, four,
five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten.
So we have 10 pair, oh, I don't
want to write that in highlight,
but 10 pairs that are here.
All right, so when it comes to
the valence electrons, let's
kind of quickly, uh, review that.
Um, it's actually, there's a quick like
little trend to kind of how to do this.
So the thing I kind of mentioned
to everybody in class for Monday,
Wednesday is you can simply
just kind of ignore the ones.
For each of the periodic tables.
So right now I'm kind of writing
over the ones on the periodic table.
Um, so if you ignore the tens position.
This is how many valence electrons
there are for each individual column
that's here on the periodic table.
So you have 3, 4, 5, 7, and 8, and
you can do the same thing on the
other side, but it's already 1, 2.
So it's 1, 5678.
So we can kind of bring
that back to normal.
But it's a, it's a, that's kind
of a quick way of really seeing it
without having to do too much work.
All right.
So predict the molecular geometry
and polarity of the SO2 molecule.
This one's kind of a hard one, um, just
because it, it violates the octet rule.
Okay, so let's see.
We were kind of split between Linear
and Ben and looks like everybody
looks like everybody for the most
part got Polar, which is good.
So let's kind of, um, take a look at this
one just because this is a trickier one.
I don't, I don't think I put
any octet rule violators on
the exam, but could be wrong.
I'm trying to recall.
I don't remember.
I think I tried to stick to just.
regular, regular structures.
So nothing that's like too, too
complicated with this particular one.
So if we are to look at this one, the
first thing we do is as write out sulfur.
So sulfur typically can
only make two bonds.
The thing is, it does have access octet.
Being that it's on the third
row of the periodic table.
So if you have third row or below,
that means it can, can, it
can violate the octet rule.
So, which is kind of
important to remember.
So it's just row three and below.
So if we put in oxygen, right, the big
thing is you can see that it won't be
happy just with doing a single bond.
It's going to have a lonely electron.
that is going to connect to
nothing, um, on the back side of it.
So if we kind of like see here,
we can, we have this electron
that's just near nothing.
So what are we going to do with
this thing that's over here?
Well, we are going to end up
moving it so that way it's
going to become a double bond.
So if I do that, we're going
to end up splitting the sulfur
lone pair on both sides.
So that way it can make two extra
bonds with oxygen on both sides.
So we're going to move
these lonely electrons and
therefore making double bonds.
So this is violating the octet rule.
You'll see that it actually has 10
electrons being shared around it.
So you got 1, 2, 3, 4,
5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10 verse.
So it's a lot.
So if we were to then look at how many
groups are there, well, there's one
on the left, one on the right, right?
And then you have the lone pair on top.
So with this one, you have
three groups, one lone pair.
So what are we going to do is we're going
to go to our handy dandy chart somewhere.
So we have three and one.
So where is that going to end up falling?
It's going to be right
here where we have 3 and 1.
So we're going on both sides to be
able to see that it's bent, and being
that it has that lone pair on the
middle of it, it's going to be polar.
And you can go off the
electronegativity too to figure
out that's polar too if you want.
That's a tough one.
Um, I don't, I think that one's a
little harder than kind of what I
have in mind for the current one.
But, you know, I'll say one thing
is not hard and then doing the
practice stuff, you know, doing
the practice exam multiple times.
It probably is only I should
try to make that bigger.
If I can, it probably is only,
uh, so useful to an extent.
I don't know, hopefully zooming
in on that helps, but so you guys
can see that a little bit better.
You should be able to see the choices on
your phone or on your computer, hopefully.
Question was, which of the, uh, which
of these Lewis structures is incorrect?
So which one is wrong,
um, is the question.
So which one of these is wrong?
And usually you're looking for two
things with wrong Lewis structures.
You're looking for octet rule violations.
Meaning too many electrons,
or too few electrons, so that
would be the first thing.
After that is, do you see any bond,
any things that aren't following
bond trends, would be the next thing.
Um, so, if you see like, um,
oxygen is making three bonds in
this case, like is that possible?
Well, it totally depends on this charge
up here, does that allow that to happen?
It might, you have to kind of
draw it out and take a look.
But Um, or like nitrogen
up at the top, right?
It has NH3.
Nitrogen can make three bonds.
So, okay.
That one looks pretty normal for D then,
you know, NH3 we've drawn already tonight.
Same thing with C with CH4.
We looked at that one too.
Same thing with B, right?
B as well is also pretty normal.
Looking at that, really the un normal
ones are the two, the A and E, which I can
understand you guys picking those ones.
So E is hydronium.
So hydronium is actually, we're
going to talk about that when
we get to acids and bases.
It's actually one of your polyatomics.
If you look at the very bottom
of the polyatomic sheet, uh, H3O
plus, that is the structure for it.
Uh, so it actually, oxygen
loses one electron, which is
why it has the positive charge.
So you see there's only five electrons
around oxygen that's started with.
So that's, um, Tony, it's one less.
With A, with Nitrogen, Nitrogen wants to
make a triple bond, so with that one, it
ends up having, um, I don't, I actually
don't think it has, it might have too
many electrons to start with, because,
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12,
yeah, so it has 12 electrons as well.
And two only has 10 electrons.
So there's actually too many
electrons for a as well.
So if you count all the dots,
you'll actually see that
there's how many atoms are in 7.
12 moles of gold.
Ooh, finally on math, our favorite.
So.
With this one, the first thing you
want to do is you want to write what
the given term is, and you've got to
think about what's the conversions
that you have available for moles.
So, it's asking you to figure
out how many atoms there are.
So, that's telling you it wants
something that's really tiny, right?
That's the entire idea
with anything with moles.
So, when we do molar conversions,
we have a few options.
We have molar mass.
which goes between grams and moles.
We have the mole to mole ratio,
okay, so which goes from like
moles of A to moles of B, right,
so whatever those two things are.
And then the last one
is Avogadro's number,
which is from moles to particles,
or when we say particles, that
could be all kinds of tiny things.
It could be atoms, it could be
molecules, formula units, uh, whatever,
you know, anything tiny, whatever
you can wrap your head around that's
really small, um, we could use it.
In this case, we're gonna
use Avogadro's number.
So it's one mole is the equivalent of 6.
022 times 10 to the 23 atoms of gold.
So when we do that, right, we
can see moles of Au cancels.
And then as a result, when you
do this problem, you're going
to see you're going to get 4.
29 times 10 to the 24 atoms of gold.
So you just multiply across.
This is the entire idea of
what we're going to do here.
It's one of those like kind of more
basic conversions, so definitely make
sure you practice your mole conversions.
There's at least, I
would say at least four.
Four to six of them on there.
There's quite a bit of them.
It's I mean the exams pretty evenly
split between everything but Those ones
are probably one of the more important
things that kind of master or later in
the semester calculate the mole the molar
mass of extra phosphorus Decoxide and they
give you the formula and it's a substance
that can be used as a drying agent So,
how would you calculate the molar mass?
So how to do this one right it's just
using your periodic table looking
up all the different values on it So
what we need to do is when you find
phosphorus, when you find oxygen,
so, uh, we can find them in the non
metals over on the right hand side.
So here's one, and then the
other one, oxygen is up here.
So all we're going to do is we're
going to, being that we had P4,
uh, O10, we're going to take 30.
97, that by 4, being that that's
part of, was your original formula,
And then you're going to then
add it to 10 oxygens times 15.
999, okay?
Now, when you end up doing that, what
you're going to get for your final
answer, so being that it's talking about
in, for molar mass, You should have 283.
88 grams per mole should
be our final unit.
Realize that those are showing in
AMU, so we should have, I should have
been showing those in molar, in grams
per mole, um, came to that problem.
Okay, so that would be how
to, how to do that problem.
Where, oh for the last
problem, where did I get the 6.
022?
So that's just your, that's
just Avogadro's number, so
that's just the constant.
So, uh, you can say you have 6.
022 times 10 to 23 of anything you
want, and that's equivalent to one mole.
So you can do that for any of your
Avogadro's number conversions.
So it's always 6.
022 times 10 to 23, whatever
thing it is, right, is equivalent
to one mole of that thing.
Ever.
It's
just, you know, we'll just
say it's the blue box 6.
022 times 10 to 23 blue boxes is
equal to one mole of blue box.
And it's whatever you need it to be.
It's a simplification, which the
following is the empirical, the
empirical formula for hexane.
So when I give you the
formula, it's C6H14.
So what is the empirical formula?
Okay.
Oh, good.
All right.
So to find an empirical formula.
So this one, right, it's
just the simplest ratio.
So you're just trying to figure
out what can you divide them
all by, by the same number.
So in this case, you can divide
them all by two in this case.
So C3H7, um, you're looking
for whatever the least common
multiple is in order to divide it.
Household sugar, sucrose,
has a molecular formula of
C12H22O11.
What is the percent of
carbon in sucrose by mass?
What is the percent of carbon in sucrose?
Well, good job to those
of you guys that got it.
This one's actually a pretty, uh,
it's a pretty tough one to be honest.
I think it's, it's a long one, uh, just
cause it involves a lot of looking up your
molar masses and all that kind of stuff.
So how do we kind of do it?
Just in case you weren't sure how to
do it or maybe just kind of guessed.
Um, so we're trying to figure out what
the percent of carbon is in this molecule.
So the whole idea is when we think
of percents is that it's defining
what is the part all over the whole.
So well, in this case,
well, what is the part?
Well, the part is carbon 12
because there's 12 carbons in
this molecule, and it's all over
C12H22O11, which is your whole, right?
So then you're just going
to times that by 100%.
So what we need to do is we need
to look up the values for carbon 12
using your periodic table, right?
Or sorry, for 12 carbons.
So all's we're going to
simply do is just take 12.
011 grams per mole.
So that's coming from the Piroc table.
We're going to times that by 12.
I'm just taking it from
number six, just taking
it from right here.
And what we're going to do is
we're going to divide that all
by the molar mass of sucrose.
So with this one, right, it's 12.
011 grams per mole times 12.
And we're going to add that
to hydrogen, which is 1.
008 grams per mole.
Times 22, and we'll add that to
oxygen, which is 11 times 15.
999 grams per mole.
So we're grabbing all those
from our table, right?
So, every single one of these.
is on the PRAC table.
So when we do that, uh, what we're
going to end up getting for our
problem is we'll have a pretty big
calculation to kind of plug in.
So you're welcome to try to, um, you
know, do one piece at a time, right?
Solve what's on top and on bottom, right?
Um, but in the end, what you will
get is that there'll be about 42.
1 percent of carbon when you divide
these two massive numbers by each other.
Okay.
This is the whole idea, right?
So you multiply everything on top
and then you want to multiply all
the stuff on the bottom and then
divide the two numbers by each other.
All right.
Which of the following is an empirical
formula of a compound that is 52.
15 percent carbon, 13.
3 percent hydrogen, and 34.
73 percent oxygen.
With this kind of problem, it might
not be a bad idea to maybe have like
the steps probably available to you.
on your notecard just because it's,
it's probably, it's arguably the longest
problem that you could have on this test.
I think, I think it would be
maybe thermochem you could argue
is longer, but I don't know.
They're pretty, they're hard.
They're really hard problems.
All right.
So the first thing that you got to
do is you got to set up the problem.
So every percent, the way that
you can actually write it is
you can write it as grams.
So now the way that you can
reason that you can do that.
Is that these, it's a, we're
making an assumption that you have
that many grams of each element
in a hundred gram sample, right?
So when you kind of add all
these up equals two, um, it's out
of a hundred is the whole idea
for it being that is a percent.
So we're making an assumption,
we're trying to figure out how much
of each mole is inside of this.
So we convert it to moles being
that's the common unit between all
elements, all substances, Okay.
So how do we go from grams to moles?
Well, that's going to be using one of
our different conversion factors, right?
So we had earlier, we can use molar
mass, mole to mole, or Avogadro's.
So in this case, we're going
to end up using molar mass,
which is our common factor here.
So we're going to once again
use the values from our
Piroc table for molar mass.
So we see that one mole of
carbon is equivalent to 12.
011 grams of carbon from your Piroc table.
Then we have 1.
008 grams of carbon is equivalent
to one mole of hydrogen.
And then we can also write
the one for oxygen 2.
Now when we solve for that,
we'll do the first one.
So it's 52.
15 divided by 12.
011.
So you should get 4.
34 moles of carbon.
Then for the next one, we
would do the same kind of idea.
So we're going to take 13.
13, and we're going to divide that by 1.
008, and we'll get about 13.
0 3 moles.
I'm just kind of rounding it just to make
it a little easier for me to write down.
Then the next one is 34.
17 divided by 15.
999 and we should get 2.
17 moles.
Now the thing with all these is that
these do represent subscripts but we
don't show, we can't have a half or
a percent or a decimal of an atom.
So what are we going to do is, We're
going to divide them all by the
smallest moles that's available.
So we're going to divide all of them,
so we're going to divide until small,
is the way that we like to phrase this.
So we'll take our individual species,
right, so oxygen was 1, right, so it's 2.
17 divided by 2.
17.
Then for carbon, it's 4.
34 divided by 2.
17, so that would be 2.
And then for hydrogen, when we do 13.
03 divided by 2.
17, we'll get roughly about 6.
So our empirical formula for this molecule
is going to end up being C2H6, and
that's how you do an empirical formula.
So the first thing is convert to moles,
then divide until small, and then you
multiply until whole if needed, right?
So we didn't have to
multiply though in this case.
So it's just like what you did
in experiment 5 and what you did
in the empirical formula videos.
So that's probably the hardest
mole problem that you could
have, something like that.
You have 5 vials, each contain
12 grams of a solid metal sample.
Which vial has the most metal atoms?
So you have calcium, platinum,
barium, gold, and zinc.
and silver.
Which one would have the most
atoms inside of the vial?
They each contain 12
grams of that substance.
When you realize the trick, you'll
see that it's actually not so bad.
So, with this one, how do you do
it is really the question, right?
You might be having.
It's a lot easier than you
might actually realize.
So, the thing that could compare
all these species is So you can
kind of go about it two ways.
You could convert everything to moles
if you want to using molar mass,
because you know that each of them
weighs 12 grams, but that's kind of
like a little too much, really all you
need to do is compare the biggest one.
and the smallest one.
So what I did here is I just,
I just boxed off where the
five were on the table, right?
So it'd be between calcium and gold.
Well, which one of them has more moles?
Because you're, you would convert
it with Avogadro's number, right?
So if you did calcium, right, if you
had 12 grams of calcium, you would
convert that using its molar mass,
and you're actually going to see
that it has a, it's a bigger ratio.
It's going to be a bigger decimal value.
That's here.
Let me take 12 divided by 40.
8.
It's going to be about 0.
299 moles of calcium, whereas
if I do gold, well, that's going
to be a lot smaller of a number.
You take 12 grams of gold, divide
that by its molar mass, which is 196.
97 grams, and convert that to moles,
and you're going to see that it's
going to be a lot smaller of a number.
It ends up being 0.
0609.
Okay.
So why do we care about this
when it asks about atoms?
Well, you would take moles and you
multiply it by Avogadro's number.
The one that would end up being the
bigger number is the one that's going
to have more atoms in your problem.
So it's going to be calcium
in this case is going to end
up having more atoms to it.
And if you need to, you can multiply it by
Avogadro's number to prove it to yourself.
But whatever has more moles
is going to have more atoms.
So you can kind of do it without
doing a ton of math if you want to.
Um, you could also see which one
is the smaller molar mass too,
if you're able to do it that way.
But only if you really, really
understand it really, really well.
Let's try this next one.
Which state of matter is described as
having a definite shape and volume?
So what has a definite
shape and a definite volume?
Theory questions, right?
This is bread and butter.
Get these right.
These are the ones you want to get right.
Um, don't overthink it, right?
Solid, it has the same shape,
no matter what, it has, it's
going to have the same volume.
So a lot easier, a little bit
easier of a problem, right?
No math.
And there is a decent number of
questions on this one that are not math.
So, which is kind of nice, um, being
that we did have a lot of theory stuff.
So make sure you're reviewing it.
If you need to put it
on flashcards, you can.
You can use your note card,
whatever you need to do.
What is the phase change
from a solid to a gas?
How do you go from a solid to a gas?
Alright, the error boost between
either sublimation or condensation.
So, a lot of those all have
to do with the gas part of it.
Um, so solid to a gas was
one of the weird ones.
That's when a, if you take something
that's solid, it immediately goes to the
gas, so it just immediately evaporates.
Um, this is sublimation.
Is what that was called to go backwards.
That would be deposition.
Um, condensation for the
person that chose purple that's
going from a gas to a liquid.
So that would be like if you have
when you have do on like your
windshield in the morning or on the
grass outside, place the substances
in order of increasing melting point.
Okay, so with this one, the stronger
the force, the higher the melting point.
So for Monday, Wednesday, this is the
extra credit video that's due on Friday.
If you haven't seen it yet, you should,
you should do it, you know, when, or
Saturday had their own extra credit video.
So this one's yours.
Okay.
So when it came to this one, the
best way to end up doing it is,
uh, it's actually based on size.
So dispersion forces, these
are all non polar when you
just see carbons and hydrogens.
nonpolar.
It's always nonpolar.
Um, so, uh, you're going to check size.
So the bigger it is, the higher the
boiling point, the melting point.
Bigger is better when it comes to
boiling point and melting point.
So you're going off the one
that's increasing in size.
So in this case, D shows that CH4 is
less than C2H4, which is less than C3H8.
So D would be, um,
phosphorus pentachloride.
It's a white solid that has a pungent
and unpleasant odor, and it's used as a
catalyst for certain organic reactions.
Calculate the number of moles in 38.
7 grams of phosphorus pentachloride.
So the very first thing that we
got to do is we're going from, it
was a really wordy problem that
really just kind of, in the end.
said that we were going to go from grams
to moles was the entire idea of this one.
So we have three conversions
we can choose from.
In this case we're going to go use
molar mass to go two grams to moles.
So we have to calculate
our molar mass for PCl.
So we got to find all of our
values from Piroc tables.
So you have one
phosphorus, five chlorines.
So what I did is I just found
the values from the Piroc tables.
So phosphorus is right here.
Chlorine is right next door, so we're
going to record those values and then
bring them down into our problem, and then
we're going to figure out our molar mass,
which you should have gotten about 208.
22 grams, and that's
equivalent to one mole of PCl5.
So now the problem said to find moles
of PCl5, and double check, yep, so
it's asking how many moles there are.
So all we're going to do
is we're going to take.
38.
7, and divide it by 208.
22, and we should get the
answer of B, which was 0.
186 moles of PCl5.
That would be our answer in that case.
So I'm just gonna get into
moles, so just a one step
conversion, this is really wordy.
A lot of times it's just
background distractor information.
What is the process in which
a molecule undergoes a phase
change from a liquid to a gas?
Easy peasy, right?
Vaporization, boiling,
you could use either term.
Um, both of them go
from a liquid to a gas.
What is the Q if 28.
6 grams of water is heated
from 22 degrees C to 78.
3 degrees C?
The specific heat of water is 4.
184 Joules per grams per Celsius.
With this one, the whole idea
is laying out the problem.
It's crucial.
So I write down all my values that I have
so that way I'm not looking at a wordy
mess every time you have a word problem.
So the first thing is is I put Delta T
in purple because usually it's kind of
where you want to start is you want to
calculate change in temperature, which
is going to be final minus initial.
So you have 78.
3 degrees C and you're in a
minus set by 22 degrees C.
and you'll get 56.
3 degrees Celsius.
Now we have every value that we need to
plug into this problem so we're going to
be kind of taking all these pieces and
plugging them into the MCAT equation.
So what we'll have is Q is equal to 28.
6 grams multiply that by 4.
184 joules grams Celsius times 56.
3 degrees C.
All right, so when, once we multiply all
those values together, um, let's see,
you end up getting E, which I'm assuming
is probably one of the kilojoule values.
So, with that, when you solve,
you'll get the following number,
so you're gonna get 6, 736.
99 joules.
And the thing is you're going to
see it doesn't match any of the
choices, but energy can either be
in joules or kilojoules or calories.
So you kind of got to be aware
of all where we're going to be.
So when it comes to kilojoules,
we simply just have to luckily
just divide by a thousand.
So 6.
736 kilojoules is going to be
what, how many kilojoules will
be when we divide by a thousand.
We round it to the correct sig figs.
And that would be our answer,
which in this case was E.
That's kind of the idea.
Let's switch back to our other screen.
How would you name the compound MgCl2?
With this question, if you find that
you really need to use the blue,
the blue naming sheet, then you, for
ionic and covalent, those are pretty
much the only type of molecules
I ask you to name on the exam.
There are no acids that you have to name.
There's no Yeah, so
there's no acid naming.
It's either going to be ionic
binary, ionic tertiary, meaning
a polyatomic, or covalent.
So just one of those three.
Um, I would really recommend you really
try to master that naming because a lot
of times chemical reaction questions
are written with the names and not the
formulas, which is really extra hard.
And you also want to be able to read
chemical bottles, and labels, and
labs, and You know, in hospitals and
places of work, so it's always helpful.
So with this one, right, um,
whenever we name a ionic compound,
we have a metal and a non metal.
Magnesium is our metal, it's our cation.
It's named first, so we say magnesium.
And being that it's bound to the anion,
chlorine, the ending changes to chloride.
So it would be magnesium chloride
would be the correct answer.
Um, with red, that's actually
referring to covalent naming.
So we use prefixes, so the di in
that case is whenever it's covalent,
meaning only nonmetals are used.
So you have to identify, is it
a metal, or is it a nonmetal?
Um, when it comes to blue, for
those that picked that one,
That's if it's a transition metal.
So if it was manganese, so MN,
then you would be maybe correct.
But being that this one is MG for
magnesium, then you got to make sure that
you, um, it has a predictable charge.
It's two plus charge.
It's always the same charge.
So a Roman numeral is not required.
Specific heat of a substance is the
amount of heat needed to do what?
What is the definition of specific heat?
Alright, so with this one, so specific
heat, the units for specific heat
are joules over gram per Celsius.
Meaning that the amount of energy,
so joules, is needed to raise the
temperature by one gram, um, of that
substance by one degree Celsius.
for this.
So it's the, the actual definition
of that particular thing.
All right, why don't you
guys try and name this one?
I'm going to go and go grab a
blue sheet and I'm going to double
check that question that was asked.
All right, so trying to name this one.
So the question was asked, what
do you exactly need for naming?
I mean, realistically, it's still
pretty much almost the whole thing.
The only thing that's
not included is acids.
So it's just that far left hand side or
so the far right hand side of the table.
So covalent binary, diatomics, you still
need to know diatomics, and then the ionic
binary and ternary are all, you know, just
that whole left hand side of the paper.
So it's still almost
everything in the end.
Um, just because they're so commonplace
in terms of chemistry, biology, and the
health sciences, it is really important
to be able to speak the language with it.
Um, so with this one, right, we would name
the metal first, just like we did before.
We would have aluminum as our
name, and then the hard part is
really remembering You know, do
you need a Roman numeral or not?
So it is aluminum sulfate.
You only need a Roman numeral when it
is a, or not a predictable element.
So in this case, aluminum
is, has a same charge.
It's a three plus charge no matter what.
So you do not need a Roman
numeral to illustrate that charge.
And usually it's only for
the transition metals.
I think aluminum's just
right outside of that.
So what is the formula
for copper One sulfide.
So copper one sulfide.
The big thing with this one
is what exactly did you do?
Do you do?
So you have copper, right?
And now the one just to
kind of color code it.
represents the charge of the molecule.
So it's copper one, right?
So plus one.
Now the next thing is we have sulfur
and we want to look up what the charge
is of that, which will be two minus.
So it's in the second
from the right column.
So we can see sulfur is right
under, right under oxygen.
So this is two minus and you have
one minus three minus, right?
So sulfur is right under that column.
So when we swap drop it, what
are we going to end up getting?
You're going to see that you're
going to have CU and you're going
to have the number two next to
it and then sulfur next door.
So CU2, we're going to trade those
value, those numbers on both sides.
Okay.
So we're going to swap drop, right?
What is the name of
CRN033?
Okay.
Most of you guys got this one.
So chromium, uh, this
one's a transition metal.
So it's not in our steps, so that
means that we'll need a Roman numeral.
Um, so when you find in the Piroc table,
it's right in the middle of the transition
metal area of the Piroc table, so it
would be chromium 3 Um, so just to kind
of go through how do you know it's 3
how do you know it's not 2 or something
like that, um, really the way to kind
of go through this kind of problem is
identifying what the charge is of the
polyatomic, or whatever's predictable,
So, being that this is our formula,
the charge of nitrate is negative one.
So what does that mean is that being
that you have three of them, so that
means you have three times negative
one, so what does the charge of chromium
need to be to balance three minus?
Well, it needs to be three plus, it
needs to be balanced on both sides.
So being that chromium, being that it's
a transition metal, does have variable
charge, we need to show it in the name.
So it needs to be chromium when you do it.
And that's another reason why I say
like, memorize the, uh, polyatomics,
because if you can get that, uh, you
can quickly see that, oh, nitrate, I
know it's Nm3, I know it's minus one.
It's like one less thing
for you to look up.
It saves you a lot of time when
it comes to tests, and it's
just less anxiety later too.
For a molecule formed from
N and Cl would be what?
So how would N and Cl bond together?
So for this problem, if you want to
draw NCl3, we did it earlier, but
in case you forgot, uh, first thing
you have to do is they are two non
metals that are bound together so that
it's not going to swap drop charges.
We need to write out
the valence electrons.
So we have nitrogen, which
has five valence electrons.
Then we have the chlorines,
which each have seven dots
or seven valence electrons.
So we're going to draw those first,
then once we draw all seven, we're going
to connect them with a single bond.
So we see that each one of these
is now connected, and this would
be your complete structure.
You would need three chlorines in
order to complete this particular
one to satisfy its octet.
That's how you do it.
The strongest interactions between
molecules of ammonia are what?
What's the strongest interaction
between Molecules of ammonia.
So you guys are a lot
of you're right, right?
It's hydrogen bonding So,
how do you know right?
So you do see that there's lone pairs
on NH3 So it definitely does dipole
dipole But if you ever see an NH in
a formula or FH or OH That's gonna be
hydrogen bonding right in this case.
We do have that NH3 that's written
in the structure So that one's
going to be, and it's going to be
hydrogen bonding is what it can do.
Uh, carbon tetrachloride
molecule, CCl4, has a what shape?
So what is the molecular
shape of carbon tetrachloride?
So with this one, right, the
whole thing with, uh, trying
to get this one just to see it.
Uh, so you guys got it
correct, which is great.
Um, we, we're going to have CCl3.
Okay.
Thank you.
So, or sorry, I say three.
ccl, four.
So we have C.
So chlorine, chlorine, chlorine.
Being that carbon can make four bonds.
We'll see that it has 1, 2, 3, 4
groups that are all around it, right?
So being that we do have those
four different groups, it's gonna
be four groups, no loan pair.
That we have our central atoms carbon.
So once again, we are
going to have tetrahedral.
The bond in CL two is a what?
It's ionic polar covalent,
non-polar or no bond at all.
So it's non-polar.
So how can you tell?
So if you look up one,
it's two non-metals.
So it cannot be ionic
when it's two non-metals.
Um, it needs to be a metal
and a non-metal to be ionic.
Um, in order to tell if it's polar
or non polar, is that they both have
the same electronegativity value.
So being that they both have an
electronegativity value, I believe, of 2.
5.
So if you take 2.
5 minus 2.
5, it equals zero.
Which is going to be, alright, choose
the best Lewis structure for OCL2.
What is the best Lewis structure for OCL2?
If you go off bonding trends,
it's a lot easier of a problem.
So let me talk about the bonding
trends briefly because I don't think
I really mentioned them earlier.
Um, the big thing with bonding trends
is that you kind of just go off how
many valence electrons there are.
So hydrogen can make one bond because
it has one valence electron to share.
Um, the second column can only has two
electrons, so it can only share two.
Um, boron only has three valence
electrons, so it can share three.
Carbon has four, so it can share four.
Now, being that we follow the octet rule,
nitrogen has 5, but it only is willing
to share 3, because it only needs 3 more
bonds to make an octet, so 3 plus 5 is 8.
Then with oxygen you need 2 more,
and then fluorine you need 1 more.
So why is that so important is
because you can see that oxygen will
make 2 bonds on each side, and it's
asking you what OCL's geometry is.
Now if we go back to like the
question, right, so seeing that we
can only make two bonds from We'll
see that the O on the green example
only has single bonds on each side.
It's the only one that only has two bonds.
All the rest either have three
or four bonds all around it, so
it's the only one that's possible
in this case to form that bond.
Okay.
The temperature of a 159 gram piece
of an unknown metal increased by 43.
4, or sorry, 43.
4 degrees Celsius.
when 6.
88 kilojoules of heat is added.
Determine the specific heat.
So we're not doing joules this
time, we're determining energy.
We're going and rearranging
our equation to get C.
Let's take a look at how to do this
one just because clearly you probably
need more time with this one, but you
know, if you were on test, hopefully
you have a few minutes to do it.
Um, we're gonna use the MCAT equation.
But the first thing what we have
to do is we're looking for C,
so it's the only thing we do.
So I listed out all the values, and
you see C is the one thing missing.
So how do we get C by itself is,
well, we gotta rearrange our equation.
So we're gonna divide by m and delta t
by both sides, that way it gets rid of m,
gets rid of delta t on the left, on the
right, and our new formula is gonna be Q
divided by m delta t is equal to So now
when we have that we want to make sure
all of our units are the right thing.
The one thing is you might notice
if you remember specific heat is
joules over grams per Celsius.
So the heat is actually needs
to get converted to joules.
So you need to multiply that by
a thousand before you can use it.
So we'll do that first and then we
can then plug it into our equation.
So 6, 880 divided by 159 grams times 43.
4 degrees C.
And this will equal our C value, so
when we end up putting that in, what
we're going to end up getting is 0.
997 joules per grams per Celsius.
And usually for most metals,
it's typically below one,
usually below one joule per gram
per Celsius for the most part.
Um, usually being that's a lot
easier to heat up a metal compared
to something like water as well.
So you could kind of take an educated
guess and probably go with like the
red, blue or green answer in this
one, um, if you were to go through it.
Okay.
So, um, this was the last
problem in the review.
Uh, so let's see who ended up winning.
I think it was Catherine.
I think she was pretty far ahead.
Um, so go through our podium and
hopefully, thank you guys for listening.
Um, good job everybody
for sticking through it.
I know this is a really long thing
to kind of sit through all the
questions and everything like that.
And I helped a little bit.
Um, so kind of going through kind of
the kind of questions you could see.
Right.
Um, just like over some of those basic
concepts and I've tried to throw in a
little bit more intermolecular forces.
So once being that I know a lot of
people are struggling with that, keep in
mind if you need to, if you need help,
you can go to ETC throughout the week.
Um, there's also grasp on Friday,
which I really recommend, um, can't
recommend it enough being that I'm
usually there for, I don't know, anywhere
from two to four hours, depending
on how many questions you guys have.
So I'm usually there starting at 10, but
the doors to grasp open as early as eight.
So if you want to get there a little
early and get help from the other
faculty there, you have that option too.
Um, I did, I did record it.
So I recorded it, um,
separately from zoom.
So everything is being recorded
through a different program.
All right.
Well, if you guys need help, reach out
to me on discord, uh, message, email me,
uh, You know, put stuff in the forum or
just direct message me whatever is easier.
I'm in office hours and I hope that I
can help you as much as I possibly can.
Okay.
Okay, everybody.
That's the end of the review session.
Thank you so much for listening.
I really appreciate you spending the
time and hopefully making it to the end.
You know, it's a lot of work making it
to the very end of the review session.
Um, on, on the actual review,
there will be some bonus problems.
So make sure you do them on that test.
Um, they might be involving, uh,
if you do watch all the way to the
end, they might be involving seven
of something that you do commonly I
have you list out using different.
Um, acronyms to help list out seven
of something so that is a hint
towards one of the bonus questions.
Um, so it's a reward
for watching this long.
All right.
Thank you all so much.
I hope you all have a wonderful
day and I will see you all later.
Bye now.